<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Army's martyr, or, A more ful relation of the barbarous and illegal proceedings of the court-martiall at White-Hall upon Mr. Robert Lockier who was shot to death in Paul's church-yard upon the 27 day of April, 1649, and a brief narrative of the cause thereof : with his Christian carriage and deportment, and his dying speeches to all his fellow-souldiers at the time of his execution as an everlasting witnesse of his integrity to the rights and freedoms of the Common-Wealth.</title>
            <author>Lockier, Robert, d. 1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25841</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3714A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24189</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08043779</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08043779</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40770</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25841)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40770)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1221:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Army's martyr, or, A more ful relation of the barbarous and illegal proceedings of the court-martiall at White-Hall upon Mr. Robert Lockier who was shot to death in Paul's church-yard upon the 27 day of April, 1649, and a brief narrative of the cause thereof : with his Christian carriage and deportment, and his dying speeches to all his fellow-souldiers at the time of his execution as an everlasting witnesse of his integrity to the rights and freedoms of the Common-Wealth.</title>
                  <author>Lockier, Robert, d. 1649.</author>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
                  <author>Overton, Richard, fl. 1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the yeer 1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"With a petition of divers well-affected persons and a letter of Lieut. Col. Jo. Lilburn, and M. Overton, presented to the General on his behalf."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trials (Military offenses) --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40770:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Army's Martyr: OR A more ful RELATION of the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and illegall Proceedings of the Court-Martiall at <hi>WHITE-HALL</hi> UPON <hi>Mr.</hi> ROBERT LOCKIER: <hi>Who was ſhot to death in</hi> Paul's <hi>Church-yard, upon the</hi> 27 <hi>day of April,</hi> 1649.</p>
            <p>And a brief Narrative of the Cauſe thereof.</p>
            <p>VVith his Chriſtian carriage and deportment, and his dying SPEECHES to all his fellow-ſouldiers at the time of his Execution, as an everlaſting witneſſe of his integrity to the Rights and Freedoms of the COMMON-WEALTH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WITH</hi> A PETITION Of divers well-affected perſons, AND A LETTER Of Lieut. Col. <hi>Jo. Lilburn,</hi> and M. <hi>Ri. Overton,</hi> Preſented To the GENERAL in his behalf.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 KING. 2.5, 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>The blood of War ſhed in the time of Peace,</l>
               <l>Cries out for vengeance; or our Freedoms ceaſe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> in the Yeer 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:40770:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:40770:2"/>
            <head>THE ARMIES MARTYR, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHereas I have been truly informed from many honeſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciencious perſons of the life and death of this gallant man M. <hi>Lockier</hi>) I thought good out of that duty I owe unto him, for to give a perfect and full Relation of the whole matter &amp; cauſe of his death, for the full ſatisfaction of all perſons that deſire to be truly informed: And knowing that it is the duty of every man that lives in a Common-wealth to be as inſtrumentall as he can, in diſcovering any thing that may be of Publick concernment; And conſidering that it is the common practice of <hi>Machiavils</hi> to colour over their cruell and unjuſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with the vizor of ſome great good, or prevention of ſome great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill to the Nation or place where the thing was committed, the better to deceive the ſimple, and wellminded people; And to keep on that veile of hypocriſie which they have caſt over the face of the Common-wealth that they might not queſtion their abominable actions, both towards this poor innocent, and their juglings with the whole Nation; I have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore taken a little paines to put forth a Narrative of the cauſe of this their bloody proceedings againſt him; that people may be poſſeſſed that their holineſſes may erre and be guilty of as much innocent blood, if they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the courſes they have walked in of late, as ever Queen <hi>Mary</hi> or any Tyrants before her: Thus then to the matter: on Tueſday <hi>Aprill</hi> the 24. 1649. there came orders for the Troop to march forth of the City; and the Souldiers being unwilling to march forth without mony to defray their Quarters: deſired pay to put them in a capacity to pay their Quarters there, and be enabled to give ſatisfaction to the Country which they were to march into: which deſires of theirs being not fulfild, they went unto the foure Swannes where their Colours were, and ſecured them for the preſent, untill they had the pay that was due to them; being invited by ſome of Cap. <hi>Groves</hi> Troop who had ſecured their colours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them: well then here was a months pay provided for them; but the Clark affirmed that there was 11 dayes pay due more to them then that months, and would have laid five pound with the Quartermaſter of the truth of it: But when Col. <hi>Whaley</hi> came and they diſputed how much they were behind, he came down the yard and ſaid there was but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40770:3"/> five dayes pay due to them: But whether this was a plot of his to cauſe this ſtirre or trouble, I know not; but ſurely it was the trick of a knave in ſo doing; but to the matter; while they were in diſpute about their mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching away, there came a fortnights pay out of <hi>Eſſex</hi> for them; and on Tueſday night there was an alarm in their quarters about ſome plot as they ſay to deſtroy the Generall and ſome Officers, and ſome papers caſt abroad to that effect, a meer plot of the Grandees as is conceived the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to countenance their illegall proceedings on ſome Citizens that night; which becauſe the Souldiers did not march were not aſhamed to put it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, though they never knew of it; at which time of the alarm, or as they were to goe to their quarters, Captain <hi>Savage</hi> told them that they ſhould come &amp; receive a fortnights pay more betimes in the morning that they might march away; whereupon they prepared for the march, ſome having received their monies; but when ſome came for it, he told them they could not, nor ſhould not receive it, though other Troops had, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they refuſed to march the day before; whereupon they kept their Colours and would not march except they were made up equall in pay with the reſt of the Regiment: But yet ſo reaſonable they were in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands that they told Col. <hi>Whaley</hi> and M. <hi>Swallow</hi> and their Capt. that if they might have but the fives dayes pay which they acknowledged was due to them, with an engagement from their Officers to pay them a days pay every day as they were upon the march till they were made up equall with the Regiment, and a paſſing by what had been done on both ſides, they would march away preſently; No, they ſhould not have it becauſe they did not march out to a Rendevouz of the Regiment the day before to Mile-end green, although there were not many above 40 of the three Troopes that marcht forth and came in againe; Yet at length Col. <hi>Wha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> ſaid that if their Captain ſhould draw out ſix men of them and carry them before the Generall, they ſhould have it: but they were unwilling that any ſhould be taken out, ſeeing all had refuſed marching: being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thereunto by their unjuſt command, in commanding them to march without their pay to ſatisfie their quarters: at length the Generall and Lieutenant Generall came very furiouſly breathing forth nothing but death to them all, being fetch'd and animated on by that forſworn and perjured tyrannicall Knave <hi>Chillington,</hi> who can take what he pleaſe out of the Souldiers pay for to maintain him in his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neering courſes. But oh how bloody and red did <hi>Cromwel</hi> look! and the Generall told them that they ſhould be hanged all, and that they did deſerve to be hanged preſently in the Court: whereupon a Souldier or two went down the Gallery, and deſired his Execellency to hear their juſt deſires:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40770:3"/> No, he would not hear them there; but they muſt march away preſently to White-hall with thoſe Troops that came to guard them thither; there being no reſiſtance offered on the Souldiers part, nor ſword drawn, though they have reported ſince, there were: but <hi>Whaley</hi> drew his, and <hi>Chillington</hi> drew his to cut a Souldier, from whoſe back he rent his cloak. But ſo much do they thirſt after the bloud of thoſe that ſhall diſpute a command of theirs, whether right or wrong, all is a caſe to them, when it comes to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh from their lawleſſe wils (for it was diſputed and affirmed by an Officer of the Army at the Spittle, that ſouldiers muſt obey their commands, and not queſtion it, though it be to kill a man, or ſteal an horſe) that to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they muſt, and the next day to a Councel of War, as they call it, where their moſt implacable &amp; bloudy enemies were their Accuſers and Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, if not their Judges; who, when they had ſworn many things againſt ſome of them which they never did (as can ſufficiently be proved by good hands) made conſtructions and conſequences on the things done and ſworn, whiſpering in the ears of them that ſate in the Councel (no queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but to ſtir up their holy zeal againſt thoſe that moſt oppoſed their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly practices.) Now though there were many witneſſes of taking the Colours from the four Swans, and carrying them into the Bul-yard; yet none ſwore, or at leaſt could ſwear, that he above any other did lay hands on them firſt, becauſe there were about 40 that huddled or compaſs'd the Colours about at one time: And though they ſay he did confeſſe himſelf he did it; I ſay, its no ſuch matter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all that he ſaid, was, that he had a hand in it as well as others. Beſides, Capt. <hi>Savage</hi> would have ſworn that M. <hi>Joyce</hi> had done it; for he came to him, and ſaid, Mr. <hi>Joyce, I will take my oath that you were the firſt man that laid hands on my Colours:</hi> But the Gentleman being not able to bear ſuch a groſſe Lie, told him, he was at the Generals Quarters that day till almoſt night to get leave to go ſee his friends.</p>
            <p>But ſuch was their former malice at this gallant man (for his former ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in the Agreement of the People, when they murdered Mr. <hi>Arnold</hi> at <hi>Ware;</hi> and becauſe he would often oppoſe or diſpute their unjuſt actions) that right or wrong, their Saint-like thirſt could be ſatisfied with nothing but his bloud. Well, die he muſt the next day by two of the clock, ſo was the Sentence; nothing could work upon any of them [for as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>There is none</hi> of them <hi>that doth good, no not one;</hi>] for when divers Citizens went with a Petition, deſiring his Excellencies mercy and clemency to mitigate the Sentence, and reprieve him but one day more; ſhewing from the Statutes of the Land, that it could be no leſſe then murder to exerciſe Martial Law in a time of peace; yet this could not prevail with him, the Law is but a dead letter to them, when they muſt exalt their wils above it;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40770:4"/> for they make no more conſcience of deſtroying the life of our lives, that is to ſay, the Law, then a dog doth of eating a ſhoulder of mutton; for their will is their Law, and their Sword their Juſtice. Another went to Col. <hi>Whaley</hi> in the behalf of this poor Innocent, and found him come lately out of bed in his Skie-colour ſatten waſtcoat lac'd with ſilver lace, and his pantophles dawbed with ſilver lace, and did preſent a Petition to his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, beſeeching his Honour, that he would be pleaſed to remember mercy to this poor Gentleman, &amp; mitigate the Sentence to any other puniſhment, ſo as it was not to the taking away of his life: But after many things paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, at laſt he ſaid, that if it lay in his power to ſave him, he would not. The like moſt humble Petition that could be framed by a man, was ſent in to the Councel on his behalf, and the reſt that were to draw lots for their lives; But nothing would ſatisfie but his blood; many perſons came to viſit him that formerly knew him much lamenting his moſt ſad condition, being condenmned for nothing but asking his pay: And indeed that was the thing which did moſt troubled him, that ſo ſmall a thing as contending for his pay, ſhould give his enemies occaſion to take away his life; which as he often ſaid, had it been for the freedom and liberties of this Nation for which he had engaged theſe 7 or 8 years, it would have much added to his comfort; Though he was ſatisfied well enough, that this in asking his pay was far inconſiderable to the taking away of his life in the eyes of God and all unprejudiced men: for he knew it was malice that prevailed over him and not juſtice; for one would have thought that there being no ſwords drawn nor affronts to any offered, that if it was ſuch a fault and of ſuch a nature, that a caſheerment of the Army, or baniſhment of the Kingdom would have been puniſhment enough for his firſt failling, and faithfull and valiant ſervices performed by him for theſe ſeven or eight years; They well knowing that for his duty he hath ever been rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to perform; and never held with any that was unwilling to do that duty which was required of him and his due to performe. Concerning his converſation, he was a man honeſt, juſt and faithfull, being able to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an account of his faith in God, and hope of eternal life; and was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo able to make good the Cauſe for which he ſo long had engaged: which is a difficult thing to many ſimple g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls now in armes, that like ſo many ſheep, will be commanded to kill and do any violence and never queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it: for indeed this is that ſweet temper theſe Machavils have ſo long laboured after; namely the caſting forth of all honeſt and deſerving Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers that would be active for common good, &amp; liſting of ſuch as will kill a man for a morſel of bread; for his civill courteſie, and loving carriage and diſpoſition at all times and to all perſons, he may challeng reſpect
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40770:4"/> from any that knew him; for I think he was beloved of many, and ſcarce hated of any; he was a man that did extremely deſire the freedom of the Common-wealth, as can be witneſſed by divers who knew his forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in promoting any thing tending thereunto: as when the agreement of the people was broken off at <hi>Ware;</hi> (by theſe that pretended it was not Gods time, becauſe they had not gotten to that height of honour which now they ſay Providence hath brought them) oh how ſad was his poor ſpirit, riding up and down the fields with one or two, where he mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted ſo much love to the liberties of his native Country, as that he could have loſt his life there to have procured it.</p>
            <p>For his valour in the field, I ſcorn to equalize it with the proudeſt of his enemies that ſate in Councell or bore falſe witneſs againſt him: he did much ſcorn to engage any man for his life, but he would endeavour his utmoſt to perform it: [Not like <hi>Whaly</hi> when he engaged Major <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thell</hi> to charge a party of the Kings Horſe, commanded by the Lord <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> neer <hi>Oxford;</hi> and promiſed to charge them with his diviſion at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place; the Major <hi>Bethell</hi> asked him again and again whether he would do it; he told him he would; who afterward ſtood ſtill and never charged at all, but ſuffered 9 troops to fall on 3 broken troops, where the Major was taken, and many kill'd and moſt deſperatly wounded; and for which he received a ſufficient check from <hi>Crumwel</hi>] he was much grieved to ſee ſuch Taxes, Exciſe, Tythes and Free-quarter to lye upon the Country, and would not be ſo exact as many ſelf ſeeking officers are (when they lye at Free quarter on the poor Country) of their accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, either for himſelf or his horſe; I need not blaze his good eſteem he had of all perſons that knew him; for they do, and can ſpeak more then I can of him, and for him: In his dealing with all men he was juſt, ever approving of that rule of Chriſt, that what we would have others do to us, we ſhould to them; and I dare pawn my Salvation upon this truth, that he did as much as could be be diſcerned, walk by it: failings I will not ſay but he was ſubject to as well as others; but if told of his failings, he indevoured amendment; and if any be without ſin let him caſt the firſt ſtone at him: ſure I am, he was more conſcionable in ſerving his Nation then Captain <hi>Savage</hi> that holy man, whoſe holineſs can admit of three men, or two men and a boy to be muſtered, and receive pay for them, and ſend them home to his father in laws houſe with their horſes and let them do their work, and the Common-wealth to pay them: But I'll war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant the good man will tell you it is a priviledge that we Officers have, being fetcht from the practice of mercenaries beyond the ſea; but this is not the firſt cheat he hath ſerved the ſtate, neither is he alone but many
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40770:5"/> more Officers in the Army, eſpecially thoſe that are married, who can make it their trade to be with their wives more then with their troops &amp; compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; though themſelves have denied that to others before they were in that Condition, telling them that he that warreth a warfare intangleth not himſelf with the things of the world. But now it is no marvell they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſe and envy every man that deſireth but to look into the myſtery of their iniquity; they may do what they pleaſe and no man queſtion them for it; as Captain <hi>Tounſell</hi> took Mr. <hi>Sawyer</hi> and caſt him into <hi>White-hall</hi> after he had abuſed him ſufficiently in his own Chamber, there commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him without any order or charge againſt him, where he might die and periſh for want of food if good people did not relieve him; ſo I ſay marvell not at their actions; for whatſoever is pleaſing in their own eyes, that they will do to any, as they have done to this true friend to his Countries Freedom. Therefore his bloud I will require at Colonel <hi>Wha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley's</hi> and <hi>Savage's</hi> hand, becauſe ſaid <hi>Whaley</hi> I knew him two yeers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this time; and <hi>Savage</hi> knew he deſired Juſtice on him when the troops charged him for diſſenting at <hi>New-market;</hi> and other articles belonging thereunto; and now have they their deſires on him.</p>
            <p>And thus have I given you a briefe narrative of the cauſe of this mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which was executed on him in <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard, where were many hundred if not thouſands, weeping eyes and ſhreking voyces lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſo gallant a creature ſhould loſe his life. What he ſaid to divers there and in his Coach coming to his execution is here inſerted verbatim, or as far as can be remembred.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Shaw</hi> and Mr. <hi>Atkinſon</hi> being come to <hi>Pauls,</hi> met with M. <hi>Lockier</hi> coming up <hi>Ludgate-hil</hi> with a ſtrong guard of Souldiers of Col. <hi>Hewſons</hi> Regiment before and behind, and he with a friend or two in a Coach, to which they addreſſed themſelves, and acquainted him with what had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed between them and the Generall; to which he anſwered, Dear friends, (he ſcarce knowing us) I am ready and willing to dye for my Country and Liberty, and I bleſſe God I am not afraid to look death in the face in this particular cauſe God hath called me to.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Atkinſon.</hi>] After that <hi>I</hi> met him in the yard where he was to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, he ſaid the ſame words, and to the ſame effect; and then the Guard driving all his friends away, and him, <hi>I</hi> could not hear what he ſaid.</p>
            <p>But <hi>I</hi> heard (getting to him through favour of an Officer) Colonel <hi>Okey</hi> to challenge him with untruth, in that he confeſſed before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of War, that he was guilty of what was charged upon him in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to mutinie, and now he denyed it: to which he anſwered that it was not ſo; <hi>Okey</hi> ſaid it was, and he could produce many to witneſſe the ſame.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40770:5"/> 
               <hi>Lockier</hi> replyed that he knew what he had ſaid well enough, and that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince he knew what it was to draw a ſword he never intended any thing but meerly for the Priviledges and Liberties of the people, and in that he would live and die, and Major <hi>Swallow</hi> and others ſaid ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to him then which <hi>I</hi> did not hear, but Major <hi>Carter</hi> made up that diſcourſe and ſaid that it was convenient that this little time he had to ſpend, it was requiſite that he ſpent it in the beſt way he thought meet and if he deſired to retire himſelf he might, to which he replyed he did deſire to retire himſelf in private, and that though he did doe or think nothing but what he would have every man to hear, for as his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from the firſt to the laſt have been for publique good, he deſired his death might be, and ſo he knew it would be: For God would make his bloud ſpeak Liberty and Freedom to all England; And then he drew to the wall, and there prayed about a quarter of an houre, and after goes and makes water, and then comes and had diſcourſe with many of the Officers, but what it was <hi>I</hi> could not well hear, but thus much <hi>I</hi> heard how he with a couragious and willing heart did undergoe what ever was laid upon him becauſe it was in the behalfe of his Country.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>I</hi> took him by the hand, and he began to ſay in this manner: friends here <hi>I</hi> am to ſuffer what it pleaſes God to lay upon me, and truly that for my Countreys good, and how great a comfort this is to me <hi>I</hi> am not able to expreſſe, and therefore friends it is a good, ſweet and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable thing for to ſerve God; for he hath ſet us in a condition to ſerve him, and given us a rule, and hath purchaſed for us not only Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Freedom here through his Son, but peace and tranquility hereafter, and a meanes he hath ſet downe in his word, which we ought to take heed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; For in that he hath declared that Chriſt is ſufficient for all our ſinnes, and God would provide fully for all thoſe that ſought to God by him: it was not any thing would commend us to God, but pure and undefiled actions in the ſight of God through the power of Chriſt and his Word which <hi>I</hi> fully own and beleeve declared the ſame, unto which we do well to take heed; for if we will we may do well here and hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: here we muſt ſerve him in ſtanding up for our Countries Liberties and Freedoms, &amp; they will make much for hereafter, for if we do well we ſhall be well rewarded. Therefore my dear friends and fellow ſouldiers, <hi>I</hi> deſire you all to ſerve God and love him, and honor him: And for me to pray as long as you ſee me live, that God would carry forth my heart as now you ſee me carried forth: to which <hi>I</hi> anſwered <hi>I</hi> am overjoyed M <hi>Lockier</hi> to hear ſuch expreſſions come from you in which <hi>I</hi> ſaw ſo much Religion, as that it was for me a good pattern <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o learn by: and not take upon me to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40770:6"/> inſtruct one ſo able as you are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Lockier</hi> ſaid, The Lord ſtabliſh and ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then you, and fit you for his work: And not onely you, but all my dear friends, to whom I deſire you to commend me dearly; to and for whom I ſhall pray while I breathe, that God would enable them to ſtand up faithfully and couragiouſly for the good of their Country and Liberties: And I pray you let not this death of mine be a diſcouragement, but rather an incouragement; for never man died more comfortably then I do. And after he and I had embraced each other, he ſpake a few words to the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and then he deſired to ſpeak with his Siſter and Couſins, but what paſſed betwixt them I know not.</p>
            <p>And then I heard not what he ſaid to them; but from good hands of them that were cloſe to him, he ſaid thus, <hi>Fellow ſouldiers, I am here brought to ſuffer in behalf of the People of</hi> England, <hi>and for your Priviledges and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and ſuch as in conſcience you ought to own and ſtand to: But I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you are appointed by your Officers to murder me; and I did not think that you had had ſuch heatheniſh and barbarous principles in you, as to obey your Officers in murthering of me, when I ſtand up for nothing but what is for your good.</hi> And then I heard Colonel <hi>Okey</hi> ſay, with other Officers, What, do you endeavour to make the ſouldiers mutinie? Martial, away with him: And ſetting him in the place where he was to ſuffer, he pulled off his looſe Jacket, and Coat, and Belt, and gave them ſome to one, and ſome to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and after that he went to prayer again in his ſhirt without his dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, and after prayer he ſtood in the place of execution, and all this while, with abundance of courage and undauntedneſs; for when I deſired him to put ſomething upon his face and cover it, he thanked me for my love, but he ſaid, his cauſe was ſo juſt, as that he feared not the face of death; and therefore he ſtood looking with a gallant courage in their faces, and then came up to the men that were to ſhoot him, which were ſix Musketiers, he lifted up his eyes to God, and deſired that when he gave them a ſigne they ſhould ſhoot, which was the lifting up of both his hands; and immediately he lifting up his hands, they all ſix ſhot off their Muskets, and ſo died this gallant Heart.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Watſon.</hi>] I asked him how it was with him in relation to his eternall condition, and whether that which he had done was not out of paſſion? and told him that he was to depart this life, the hour of his death was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neer, therefore I deſired him if any thing lay upon his Spirit that he would declare it to me; he replyed, I have been a ſervant to them a long time, and been faithfull, I am burdened in my Spirit becauſe of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt proceedings, and for my condition at preſent, I praiſe God it is well with me, and I praiſe God out of obedience to God, I have ſerved my
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40770:6"/> Country and for that I firſt ingaged, I little thought that they would have proceeded ſo harſh againſt me to ſingle me from the reſt of my fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, the fault being one and the ſame; not that I am ſorry that I am ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out by my ſelf, for I am joyfull that I muſt dye to excuſe them, but I ſee their aime is at my blood, and when they have it they may then be ſatisfied, though that will give them little ſatisfaction as to righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yet I praiſe God I am fitted for it and have a witneſſe from God that I have ſerved my generation with uprightneſſe ſo farre as I had underſtanding, and ſeeing God hath been ſo pleaſed to diſpoſe of me, let it come and welcome, death is nothing, it ſtoppeth my progreſſe from ſorrow to ſorrow, I am ſure I have a ſmiling conſcience within me and the love of the Father made out to me through the Son, and for death I praiſe God I fear it not, and ſo dear friend I leave thee to the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of the Almighty hoping to meet thee in word, <hi>I</hi> meane in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, though now we are divided by death; <hi>I</hi> deſire you would joyne in prayer with me, which we did.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Bunting</hi> told him, That he had heard very well of him, that he was an honeſt conſciencious man, and that much of God appeared in him, for which he was glad; now he was appointed to die, it was good for him to make preparation, he having been one of the chief promoters of the late mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinie, which might have occaſioned the ſhedding of much bloud, for which he was ſentenced by the Councel of War to be ſhot; and ſaid that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel was very tender in their dealing towards them, and that they deſired not to ſhed bloud; though there were 14 more guilty, yet but him to die: however his intention might be good, yet a Mutinie being of ſuch an high nature, could be adjudged no leſſe then death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Sir I am condemned, or brought here to dye, I bleſs my God I can freely ſubmit unto it, having learned to look death in the face, hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the merits of the Lord Jeſus to have life and ſalvation; I have done nothing whereof I am accuſed; I am ſentenced as I think by their ſixt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle to ſuffer. An Officer then ſtept in and ſaid that he did before the Councel acknowledge that he was the chief of the mutinie; which mutinie deſerved death: which preſently was denied, ſaying that he was no more concerned then the reſt, and for them to take away his life, was very partiall and unjuſt; but I pray God forgive them, and us all our ſins, that it be not laid to their charge; I am ſure their dealings with me is bloody for them to take away my life for a ſuppoſed crime, for that which might happen; beſides I never went forth to uphold a Martiall Law to be executed in a time of peace, it being too cruel for any freeborn Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to live under: I went voluntarily forth being invited by declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40770:7"/> of Parliament, to ſtand by them in the defence of the juſt rights and freedoms of this Nation, for which I have engaged my life, and for the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and liberties of the people, I now ſuffer. An Officer ſteps in and ſaid it was in your own choice you might have left the Army if you would, for why ſhould you continue under the power of it and not to obey. <hi>Anſ.</hi> I am ſure I have been faithful I never betray'd my truſt. Severall of the Officers deſiring him to retire, if poſſible they might diſturbe him, it may be he would be private, the time is but ſhort, therefore think of death. <hi>I</hi> bleſs the Lord <hi>I</hi> can willingly ſubmit to dye; he then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew for a while and prayed, and came again diſcourſing a little with the Officers; called for his Siſter and Friends there, came to the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers that were to ſhoot him, and ſaid, <hi>I</hi> freely forgive you and all the world; I pray ſiſter forgive them. <hi>I</hi> am ſorry to ſee that you ſhould be brought to obey your officers to murther me, for you ſtand as if you were the men appointed to murder me; <hi>I</hi> pray God forgive you <hi>I</hi> doe: Whereupon the Officers thruſt him away, and ſaid he would make a muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie among the Souldiers take him away; ſo being not permitted to ſpeak to them, they ſhot him, &amp;c. ſaying they were ſorry to ſee him dye ſo. A mutineer he lived, and ſo he died.</p>
            <p>But as he was honorable in his life and at his Death; ſo he was as honorably buried to the trouble of many of his enemies, who could have been contented to have his memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall to be buried in oblivion, that their wickedneſſe might not be had in remembrance: But I beleeve he did not ſo much offend them in his life, but his death ſhall be a greater terrour to them in crying for vengeance on their heads: the guilt of whoſe blood doth trouble many of them already as I hear: However he is gone to his grave in peace with confidence in Gods love tto him through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> where he ſhall reſt in his grave and at laſt ſtand up in his Lott having his Portion amongſt the Juſt, and crowned with the loving kindneſſes and enjoyment of God.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="petition">
                        <head>To his Excellency THOMAS Lord <hi>FAIRFAX</hi> Generall of the Engliſh Forces. The humble addreſſes of divers well affected perſons, in behalfe of all thoſe that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der reſtraint or cenſure of the Councel of War, or Law-Martiall.</head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>May it pleaſe your Excellency,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>FOraſmuch as the Petition of Right, and other the known Laws of the Land do expreſly provide againſt the exerciſe of Martiall Law upon Souldiers or others in times of peace, all Courts of Juſtice being open, and that the deprivation of life thereby in ſuch times hath been adjudged in Law no leſſe then murther.</p>
                        <p>And foraſmuch as you have declared to all the world, That the Army under Your Excellency's Command was not a meer mercinary Army, hired to ſerve the Arbitrary ends of a State; but that they took up arms in judgement and conſcience, for your own and the Peoples juſt Rights, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall whereof are contained in the foreſaid Laws and Petition of Right.</p>
                        <p>And finding nevertheleſſe thoſe our undoubted Liberties never more encroached upon by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary power and Law-Martial, Souldiers and others of late being frequently ſeized, reſtrained and adjudged to death, and to reproachfull puniſhments without any regard to the Law of the Land, and tryall of twelve ſworne men of the neighbourhood: as is manifeſt in your preſent proceedings againſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40770:7"/> thoſe Souldiers and others now under reſtraint, and cenſure of the Councell of war.</p>
                        <p>Hereupon we conceive our ſelves bound in conſcience in behalf of the Liberties of the people of England to intreat and claim the benefit of thoſe Liberties contained in the Petition of Right, and other the good Lawes of this Land: and that all perſons now under reſtraint or cenſure of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of War or Martiall Law, may be remitted to the tryall of twelve ſworn men of the neighbourhood, and be proceeded againſt by due proceſſe of Law; which I humbly conceive your Excellency and the whole army, are both by Law, and your many Declarations engaged to perform, and whereby only you will render your ſelf acceptable to the preſent, and honorable to future Generations.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Robert Shaw</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Thomas Moulſon</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>George Atkinſon</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Thomas Hawes</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Thomas Frisbe</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Walter Allen.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </signed>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Aprill <hi>27. 1649.</hi>
                              </date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>M. <hi>Robert Shaw</hi> and the reſt went with this Petition, &amp; after that came to <hi>White-hall,</hi> &amp; there related to the priſoners what they had done in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, &amp; then M. <hi>Atkinſon</hi> addreſſed himſelf, at M. <hi>Lockiers</hi> requeſt to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhall General, &amp; acquainted him with the particular carriage in the buſineſs how they had drawn up a Petition to the General, and did deſire he would ſtay till they had an Anſwer. He replyed, that if ſo, they ſhould wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Generall for an anſwer, and meet him at <hi>Pauls,</hi> for there he was appointed to ſuffer. And to that end Mr. <hi>Shaw,</hi> Mr. <hi>Atkinſon</hi> and others went to the Generall, whom they found at <hi>Grays</hi> Inn in Sir <hi>Thomas Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thringtons</hi> Lodgings, and with much adoe were admitted to ſpeak with him: Unto whom Mr. <hi>Atkins</hi> ſpake to this effect; May it pleaſe your Excellency, We are come in the behalf of a poor diſtreſſed man that is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed this day, and almoſt ready to die: in whoſe behalf we only deſire your Excellency be pleaſed to pardon, or but to reprieve him till to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. And we are the rather incouraged thereunto by Reaſon of your wonted mercy in this particular. To whom he replyed, You come here about the ſaving of a ſouldier, who is already condemned by the Councell of Officers under me, and for a great crime of mutinie, wherein were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged many more beſides him, at leaſt 15; and I think, in ſuch a high bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe as this is, you never knew a Generall to pardon ſo many as I have done; and now he is to ſuffer by courſe of Martiall Law, and it being paſt, it cannot be recall'd. To which we anſwered, Your Excellency hath ſhewen much mercy to poor men in the like nature, that did deſerve more to die then he did: Therefore we were imboldened to ſue to your Excellency for him, to which he anſwered, That he conceived he deſerved to ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r as he did, and that it did behove us, if we were his friends, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare him for another world; and not to do as we do, to countenance him in any thing that is not regular nor ſafe; for he had like to have made a great fraction in the City and Army, and for that he is to die, and it lies not in my power to preſerve him. Then we did beſeech his Excellency to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieve him but till to morrow: but he would not condeſcend to neither. And ſo much paſſed to this effect, but nothing at all obtained from him.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:40770:8"/>
                  <head>The Copy of a Letter written to the Generall, from Lieut. Col. <hi>Jo. Lilburn</hi> and M. <hi>Rich. Overton,</hi> Arbitrary and Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocratical priſoners in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> the 27 of <hi>April</hi> 1649, in behalf of Mr. <hi>Robert Lockier,</hi> tyrannically ordered to be murdered by the pretence of Martiall Law by the Councel of War at White-Hall: M. <hi>George Aſh,</hi> M. <hi>Joſeph Hockley,</hi> M. <hi>Robert Osburn,</hi> Mr. <hi>Matth. Heyworth,</hi> Mr. <hi>Tho. Goodwin,</hi> all of Captain <hi>Savage</hi> his Troop in Col. <hi>Whaley</hi>'s Regiment; who by the ſaid Councel were adjudged to caſt lots for their lives, and one of them to die.</head>
                  <head type="sub">In which it is by Law fully proved, That it is both Treaſon and Murder, for any General or Councel of War to execute any Souldier in time of Peace, by Martial Law.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it pleaſe your Excellency,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WEe have not yet forgot your Solemn Engagement of <hi>June</hi> 5. 1647, <hi>whereby the Armies continuance as an Army was in no wiſe by the will of the State, but by their owne mutuall Agreement:</hi> and if their ſtanding were removed from one Foundation to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as is undeniable) then with the ſame they removed from one Authority to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; and the <hi>Ligaments and Bonds of the firſt were all diſſolved,</hi> and gave place to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; and under, and from the head of their firſt Station, <hi>viz. By the will of the State, the Army derived their Government by Martiall Law;</hi> which in Judgment and Reaſon could be no longer binding then the Authority (which gave being thereto) was binding to the Army: for the denyal of the authority is an Abrogation and Nulment of all Acts, Orders, or Ordinances by that Authority, as to them: And upon this account your Excellency with the Army <hi>long proceeded upon the Conſtitution of a new Councell and Government,</hi> contrary to all <hi>Martiall Law</hi> and Diſcipline, by whom only the Army engaged to be ordered in their proſecution of the ends, to wit, <hi>Their ſeverall Rights both as Souldiers and Commoners, for which they aſſociated; Declaring, agreeing, and promiſing each other, not to Disband, Divide, or ſuffer themſelves to be Disbanded or Divided, without ſatisfaction, and ſecurity, in relation to their Grievances and deſires in behalfe of themſelves and the Common-wealth, as would be agreed unto by their Councel of Agitators.</hi> And by vertue, &amp; under color of this Eſtabliſhment, all the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Actions by your Excellency, your Officers, and the Army have paſt: Your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſall to Disband, diſputing the Orders of Parliament; Impeachment and ejection of Eleven Members; your Firſt and Second March up to <hi>London;</hi> your late violent Excluſion of the major part of Members out of the Houſe, and their impriſonment without Cauſe declared, &amp;c. <hi>which can no way be juſtified from the guilt of high Treaſon, but in the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a righteous end,</hi> viz. <hi>The enjoyment of the benefit of our Laws and Liberties, which we hoped long ere this to have enjoyed from your hands:</hi> Yet when we conſider, and herewith compare many of your late carriages both towards the Souldiery and other Free-People; and <hi>principally your cruell exerciſe of Martiall Law,</hi> even to the Sentence and execution of Death upon ſuch of your Souldiers as ſtand for the Rights of that Engagement, &amp;c. And not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo, but againſt others not of the Army; we cannot but look upon your <hi>Defection</hi> and <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> in ſuch dealings, as of moſt dangerous conſequence to all the Lawes and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the People.</p>
                  <p>And therefore, although there had never been any ſuch ſolemn Engagement by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, as that of <hi>June</hi> 5. 1647. which with your Excellency in point of duty and conſcience ought not to be of the meaneſt obligation, <hi>We do proteſt againſt your Exerciſe of Martial Law, againſt any whomſoever, in times of Peace, where all Courts of Juſtice are open,</hi> as the greateſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40770:8"/> encroachment upon our Lawes and Liberties that can be acted againſt us; And particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, <hi>against the Trial of the Souldiers of Captain</hi> Savage's <hi>Troop yeſterday,</hi> by a Court Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, upon the barbarous Articles of Warre, and ſentencing of two of them to death; and for no other end (as we underſtand) but for ſome diſpute about their pay: And the reaſon of this our Proteſtation, is from the Petition of Right, made in the third yeer of the late King, which declareth, <hi>That no perſon ought to be judged by Law Martiall, except in times of Warre; And that all Commiſſions to execute Martiall Law in times of Peace, are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Lawes and Statutes of the Land.</hi> And it was the Parliaments complaint, That <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Law was then commanded to be executed upon Souldiers for Robbery, Mutiny, or Murder.</hi> Which Petition of Right, this preſent Parliament in their late Declarations of the 9. of Feb. and the 17 of March 1648, <hi>commend, as the moſt excellent Law in</hi> England, and there promiſe to preſerve inviolably, it, <hi>and all other the fundamentall Laws and Liberties, concerning the preſervation of the Lives, Properties and Liberties of the People, with all things incident there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</hi> And the Exerciſe of Martiall Law in Ireland, in time of Peace, was one of the chiefeſt Articles for which the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> loſt his head; as appears Article 1, in the caſe of the Lord <hi>Mount-Norris</hi> (yet alive:) the ſame by this preſent Parliament being judged high Treaſon. And the Parliament it ſelf, neither by Act nor Ordinance, can juſtly or warrantably deſtroy the fundamental Liberties and Principles of the Common Law of England: It being a <hi>maxime</hi> in Law and Reaſon both, <hi>That all ſuch Acts and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances are</hi> ipſo facto <hi>null and void in Law, and bind not at all, but ought to be reſiſted and ſtood againſt to the death.</hi> And if the ſupreme Authority may not preſume to do this, much leſſe may You, or Your Officers preſume therupon; for where remedy may be had by an ordinary courſe in Law, the party grieved ſhall never have his recourſe to extraordinarie. Whence it is evident, <hi>That it is the undoubted Right of every Engliſhman</hi> (Souldier or other) that he ſhould be puniſhable onely in the ordinary Courts of Juſtice, according to the Laws and Statutes of the Realm in the time of Peace, as now it is (there being no declared enemy in arms either in field or garriſon ready to deſtroy the Nation with fire and ſword, and by their fury and power ſtop or dam up the ordinary adminiſtration of the Law) and the extraordinary way by Court Martiall, in no wiſe to be uſed.</p>
                  <p>Yea, the Parliaments Oracle, Sr. <hi>Ed. Cook,</hi> Declares in the third part of his <hi>Inſtitutes</hi> Cap. of <hi>Murther,</hi> fol. 52. <hi>that for a General or other Officers of an Army in time of Peace to put any man, (although a Souldier,) to death, by colour of Martiall Law, it is abſolute murther in that Generall, or Councel of War, &amp;c.</hi> Becauſe, ſaith he, this is againſt <hi>Magna Charta, ch</hi> 29. and is done by ſuch power and ſtrength as the party cannot defend himſelf: and here the Law implyeth <hi>malice; vide Paſch.</hi> 14 <hi>fol</hi> 3. <hi>in Scaccario,</hi> The Abbot of <hi>Ramſey</hi>'s Caſe, in a Writ of Errour, in part abridged by <hi>Fitzh. tit. Scire fac.</hi> 112 for time of peace. <hi>Thomas</hi> Earl of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> being taken in an open Inſurrection, was by judgment of Martial Law put to death: <hi>in anno</hi> 14. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. this was adjudged to be unlawfull, becauſe (ſaith he) he was not arraigned or put to anſwer in the time of peace; and becauſe the Chancery, and all other Courts of the Kings were then open; in which Law was done to every man, as it wont to be; and that againſt the Charter of <hi>Liberties,</hi> becauſe the ſaid <hi>Thomas</hi> being a Peer and Noble of the Kingdom, ſhould not be impriſoned, nor ſhould the ſame King paſſe Sentence upon him, but by the lawfull judgment of his Peers: yet in the time of peace, and without Arraignment or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, or lawful Judgment of his Peers, he was adjudged to death. Therefore erecting of Martiall Law, now, when all Courts of Juſtice are open, and ſtopping the free current of Law, which ſufficiently provides for the puniſhment of Souldiers as well as others (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by 18. H. 6: Ch. 18, 19. and 2, &amp; 3. Ed. 6. Ch. 2. 4 &amp; 5. P. &amp; M. Ch. 3. &amp; 5. Eliz. 5. &amp; 1. Jam. 25.) is an abſolute deſtroying of our Fundamentall Liberties, and the razing of the Foundation of the Common Law of England; the which out of duty and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Rights and Freedoms of this Nation (which we value above our lives) and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> You and all Your Councell without all excuſe, we are moved to preſent unto your
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40770:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> Excellencie: Earneſtly preſſing you, well to conſider what you doe, before you proceed to the taking away the lives of thoſe men by Martiall Law; leaſt the blood of the Innocent, or the blood of War ſhed in the time of peace (and ſo palpable ſubverſion of the Laws and Liberties of England) bring the reward of juſt vengeance after it upon you, as it did up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Joab</hi> the Son of <hi>Zerviah,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 33. and the Earl of Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford: for innocent blood God will not pardon, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.5, 6. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.10. and which cannot be expiated but by the bloud of him that ſhed it, <hi>Numb.</hi> 35.33. <hi>Deut</hi> 19.11, 12, 13. and 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.12. and 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.19. and 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9.7, 8, 9, 10, 26, 33, 36, 37. and <hi>chap.</hi> 24.2, 3, 4. and what the people may do (in caſe of ſuch violent ſubverſion of their Rights) we ſhall leave to your Excellency to Judge, and remain</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     <signed>Your Excellencies moſt watchful obſervers
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Iohn Lilburn.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Richard Overton.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>From our Cauſeleſſe, unjuſt, and Tyranical Captivity in the Tower of London, <date>April 27. 1649.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>The POSTSCRIPT to the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Countryman,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE deſire thee to take notice, that M. <hi>Robert Shaw,</hi> M. <hi>Thomas Moulſon,</hi> M. <hi>George Atkinſon,</hi> M. <hi>Thomas Harris,</hi> M. <hi>Thomas Frisby,</hi> and M. <hi>Walter Allen,</hi> delivered a Petition to the Generalls own hands, to the effect of this Letter, divers houres before the execution of the foreſaid gallant and honeſt M. <hi>Robert Lockier;</hi> which Petition and the Generals anſwer, you may at large read in the 3 and 4 pages of the Book called the <hi>Armyes Martyr:</hi> But nothing would ſatisfie the Generall but his innocent bloud; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore according to the Law of his will, he cauſed him to be murthered or ſhot to death in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard; for whoſe innocent blood, both by the Law of God and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome the Generals ought to go without mercy or compaſſion; and not only his but alſo all the reſt of his Judges and Executioners, for which by the Law of England they are indictable (by any honeſt Engliſh man) in the County where the murther was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. And that this Act in ſhooting precious Maſter <hi>Lockier</hi> to death, is not only will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mutrher in the eye of the law of England, but alſo Treaſon, is plainly and undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly proved, in C. <hi>Iohn Ingrams</hi> plea, M. <hi>Wil. Tompſons</hi> plea, and M. <hi>Io. Croſinans</hi> plea, all of which are printed at large in Lieutenant Col. <hi>Iohn Lilburns</hi> Book, Printed, <hi>Feb,</hi> 1647. and called, <hi>The Peoples Prerogative,</hi> pag. 44, 45, 46, 47, 48, 49, 50, 51, 52, 53, 54, 55, 56. And alſo in his additions to his ſecond Edition of his Book called, <hi>The Picture of the Councell of State:</hi> And therefore let us tell the Generall, It may prove in time a vaine thing to him and his officers to protect themſelves with their ſwords from the due courſe and proceedings of Law; leaſt the people come to preach the ſame doctrine to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and his Tyrannicall officers, that their darling friend the preſent Lord Chief Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice St. <hi>Iohn</hi> preached to the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> in the latter end of his Argument of Law Printed for <hi>Iohn Bartlet,</hi> and made againſt him when he was upon his Tryall, whoſe words are theſe, <hi>That he in vaine calls for the help of the Law, that walks contrary unto Law, and from the Law of life for life; he that would not have others to have law, why ſhould he have any him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? why ſhould not that be done unto him, which he himſelfe would have done to another? It is truth ſaith he, we give law to Hares and Deer, becauſe they be Beaſts of Chaſe; but it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver accompted either cruelty or foule play to knock Foxes or Wolves on the head as often as they can be found, becauſe they be beaſts of prey; The warrenner ſets traps for Polcats and other vermine for the preſervation of the warren,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>JOHN LILBURN.</item>
                     <item>RICHARD OVERTON</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Tower,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>May,</hi> 4, 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
